Guide to the Edin Vâelez Papers and videos, 1970-1994
Department of Special Collections
Edin Vâelez Papers and videos,
1970-1994
M0933
Vâelez, Edin
6 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
A pioneer in video art, Vâelez, together with Gary Hill and Bill Viola, was at the forefront of the generation that established video as an art form in the 1970s.
Administrative Information
Access
The Media materials require at least two weeks advance notice to use in order to allow staff time to have use copies made from the original items.
Acquisition Information
Purchased, 1997.
Provenance
Purchased, 1997.
Biography
Educated at the University of Puerto Rico, where he was influenced by Marshal McLuhan, Vâelez subsequently moved to New York where he studied at Global Village. Vâelez has been credited with the development of "a new transequential language of representation," in which multiple scenes are superimposed and juxtaposed within the frame. In this respect, Vâelez's production notes on his video pieces provide a unique and invaluable resource on how he was able to make these advances using analog formats -- nearly a decade before digital formats made layered imagery a standard practice in video production. In his numerous videos, Vâelez has explored other cultures -- from the Cuna Indians of Panama to the Butoh dancers of Japan -- using his unique video aesthetic and language to explore intercultural dialogue and self-reflexive ethnography. Above all, Vâelez's videos attest to the impossibility of a one-to-one translation across cultural boundaries. (Extracted from notes by Chon Noriega, Dept. of Film and Television, UCLA)
Collection Scope and Content Summary
Correspondence, scripts, business papers, original artwork, and production stills related to videos. Twenty completed video works, nearly half of which are out of distribution, 51 hours of video documentation including "Behind the Scenes," a 19-hour documentary of the production process for two key works: A MOSQUE IN TIME and MEMORY OF FIRE, and a 32-hour documentary of Japanese Butoh dance, and last, video copies of television interviews with Vâelez for Spanish, Argentinian, and Japanese television.
Access Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Butåo.; Cuna Indians.; Modern dance--Japan.; Video art.; Video recordings.
Collection Contents
- Series 1. Papers
  - 1. Notebook 1987-881987-1988 (Box 1)
    30 pages 4 handwritten ideas, notes, many sketches of installations, objects,books storyboards for tapes never shot, original notes for "Memory of Fire" (not named as such), notes on art, ect.
  - 2. Meaning of the Interval" edit notes, file 2, 19861986, 96 manuscript sheets,4 photo contact sheets (Box 1)
    Sketches and br storyboards explore how to combine different scenes in one frame. Most of the sketches are done in colored marker, the given color used as a code for the type of scene (i.e.:religious, modern,traditional, etc.) includes hand drawn stencils for Japanese words used as key elements, and hand drawn wipe templates. Very complete documentation of the editing process of one of the first videos made using multiple simultaneous layers of images in collage fashion. most pages are dated so one can follow the process of layering. Also, 4 photographic contact sheets that have every major scene used in the editing. This method of visually storing the key frame of every scene will be used by Ev to keep a record of very scenee in every tape from this point on.
  - 3. Color photocollage for Meaning of the Interval postcard made in the style of the video, 19871987 (Box 1)
  - 4. "Meaning of the Interval" edit notes, file 1, 1985-86, 34 manuscript sheets see number 2 above for description (Box 1)
  - 5. "Dance of Darkness" edit notes, spiral bound notebook, 1988, 36 pages (Box 1)
    Mostly manuscript, a few typescrpit logs with detailed annotations at margins. Many sketches and storyboards for multi-layering edit. many pages but not all dated.
  - 6. Two architectural renderings of 3 channel video installation: "Naruhodo", Drawings are originals (1987?) pencil on vellum, 11" by 16" -Also, four high qualty xeroxes (originals lost) of sketches leading up to final drawings 11" by 16" Installation not yet completed. (Box 1)
  - 7. Eight pages, manuscript on grid paper, color coded for final audio mix: Dance of Darkness. (Box 1)
    Shows every audio layer of final tape individually, 7 audio tracks with descriptions.
  - 8. Dance of Darkness, edit notes file, 38 pages 1988-89 (Box 1)
    Includes all translations,transcripts, annotatde. Original ink Drawings for title card in English and French.
  - 9. "The Date" 1988, 11 pages,62 cards 2 by 4 with scene descriptions (and written) Handwritten diagrams delineating a multi layered narrative. Precursor to Hypertext, and CD rom.Dot matrix sceond version included which has changes.project not completed (Box 1)
  - 10. Guatemala Video Logs, 1988, 29 pages video logs with notations,one manuscript page with sketches/storyboards (Box 1)
    For a edit of footage shot in Guatemala while making Meta Mayan to be used in a new video. Video logs are pages that have 12 images from original footage. original scenes printed from video using video printer then fitted on one page and xeroxed.-project not completed. NOTE: whenever I use the term "video log" it refers to these visual, not text, pages. Each page has color coded markings as to how certain parts of images would be used in layers with others.
  - 11. Signal to Noise: video logs with notations, 14 pages 1989,10 original thermal video printouts. (Box 1)
    For not completed autobiographical video.
  - 12. Memory of Fire: 6 Scripts 1990,92,93, (79 pages) (Box 1)
    original treatment submitted for funding to ITVS in 1990 subsequent scripts each with amjor changes 1992 through 1993 shows evolution of film very clearly
  - 13. Memory of Fire: Fax correspondence between EV and producers of film 93-94, 24 sheets including original faxes received from producers. (Box 1)
    This correspondence was 2/3 during production when relationship between EV and producers deteriorated and communication was solely via fax. A number of major issues and problems are discussed.
  - 14. Memory of Fire: (Box 1)
    5 manuscript sheets early multi layer storynoards for film, never realised, as well as illustrated character descriptions, and flying boat sketch, never realised.
  - 15. Memory of Fire (Box 1)
    9 sheets,set design EV in colab. with designer Mark Stieger 1 by 16 xeroxes, ,with handwritten notations by EV (originals lost) for sets, never realised.
  - 16. Memory of Fire, 9 sheets, character and costume designs EV in colab. with designer Mark Stieger, 8 by 11 xeroxes ( orig. lost) with EV notations. never realised. (Box 1)
  - 17. Memory of Fire, 9 sheets, Art Dir. plans for actual sets, 11 by 16 xeroxes, orig lost, no notations (Box 1)
  - 18. Memory of Fire, 14 sheets, 8 by 11 xeroxes of images used as references in original script, copies of engravings and paintings. Notations as to scene no. etc. (Box 1)
  - 19. Memory of Fire (Box 1)
    Scene breakdown script, no notes, 1993 14 pages Lists actors,action, set, props ,etc for every scene in script
  - 20. Memory of Fire (Box 1)
    Editing notes file, 10 handwritten sheets with notes ,sketches and storyboards; Scribe scene completely annotated script section(3 sheets). Court of the Queen script section (3 sheets) annotated. 5 foot by 2 foot handwritten chart on grid paper showing all music and audio and track assigned (8 audio tracks),color coded and notated.
  - 21. A Mosque in Time: Edit file: 1990, 14 handwritten pages with multi layer sketches, and edit notes. 11 pages of video logs with notation (Box 1)
  - 22. Fura dels Baus: correspondence (Box 1)
    3 letters to and from the Spanish performance group La Fura Dels Baus about collaborating on a video on Columbus, 1991, as well as literature on the group
  - 23. Revelaciones (Box 1)
    Edit notes (7 handwritten pages). video logs with notations 32 pages 1994
  - 24. Dance of Darkness (Box 1)
    Interview transcripts with all dancers, 82 pages
  - 25. Dance of Darkness (Box 1)
    Final selects video logs with notations, and some color coding 43 sheets,2 handwritten note sheets.
- Series 2. Videotapes, 56 one hour U-Matic Videocassettes.
  The Media materials require at least two weeks advance notice to use in order to allow staff time to have use copies made from the original items.
  - Kazuo Ohno interview, Pt 2 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Ohno int., Pt 3 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Ohno int., Pt 4 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Dairakudakan, port perf. no audio (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Dairakudakan, port perf (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Dairakudakan, beach perf (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Ohno, Dead Sea Performance, pt 1 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Ohno, Dead Sea Performance, Pt 2 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Ohno, Dead Sea Performance, pt 4 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Ohno, Siren Performace, pt 2 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Ohno. Mother perf., part 1 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Ohno, Mother perf., part 2 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Ohno, Mother perf., pt 3 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Ohno, rehearsal at home pt 1 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Ohno, rehearsal at home pt 2 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Ohno, rehearsalat home Pt 3 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Ohno, rehearsal at home Pt 4 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Ohno, Interv. pt 1 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Ohno, La Argentina Perf. Pt. 1 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Ohno, La Argentina Perf. Pt 2 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Ohno, La Argentina Perf. Pt 3 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Ohno, Interv. Pt 5 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Ohno, Mother, reh. Pt 1 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Ohno, Mother, reh. Pt 2 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Ohno, Mother makeup, Argentina reh. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Ohno, La Argentina makeup (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Ohno, Dead Sea reh. Pt 1, La Argentina reh. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Ohno, La Argentina reh. 2 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Ohno, Dead Sea reh. Pt 2 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Ohno, Dead Sea reh. pt 3 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Dai Rakuda Kan perf. Durham N.C. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Dai Rakuda Kan, perf Tokyo 1984 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Dai Rakuda Kan, perf Tokyo 1984 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Dai Rakuda Kan, perf Tokyo 1984 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Dai Rakuda Kan, perf Tokyo 1984 women's group (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Dai Rakuda Kan, perf Tokyo 1984 women's group (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Dai Rakuda Kan, perf Tokyo 1984 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Dai Rakuda Kan, perf Tokyo 1984 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Dai Rakuda Kan, perf Tokyo 1984 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Dai Rakuda Kan, perf Tokyo 1984 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Dai Rakuda Kan, perf Tokyo 1984 women's group (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Dai Rakuda Kan, perf Tokyo 1984 women's group (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Hljikata, Rebellion of the Body, archival film 1968 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Donald Richie, mt. (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Ichikawa, mt. (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Dai Rakuda Kan, perf Tokyo 1984 women's group (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Dai Rakuda Kan, perf Tokyo 1984 women's group, no audio (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Dai Rakuda Kan, perf Tokyo 1984 women's group, audio starts halfway (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Dai Rakuda Kan, perf (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Dai Rakuda Kan, Port perf. no audio (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Ohno, Dead Sea perf. Pt 1 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Ohno, Dead Sea perf. pt 2 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Ohno, Dead Sea perf. Pt 3 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Dai Rakuda Kan, Port perf. (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - DaiRakudaKanBeachperf. (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Dai Rakuda Kan, Temple Steps perf. (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Dai Rakuda Kan, temple steps cutaways (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Dai Rakuda Kan, Shinjuku perf. (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Dai Rakuda Kan, Shinjuku perf. (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Akiko Motofuji Interv. (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Akaji Maro, interv Pt 1 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Akaji Maro, interv Pt 2 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Dai Rakuda Kan workshop, NYC (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Dai Rakuda Kan, Durham, N.C. perf pt 1 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Dai Rakuda Kan, Durham, N.C. perf Pt 3 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Dai Rakuda Kan, Durham, N.C. perf pt 4 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Dai Rakuda Kan, Durham, N.C. perf Pt 5, Charles Reinhardt interv. (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Dai Rakuda Kan, Durham, N.C. perf Pt 6 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Dai Rakuda Kan, Durham, N.C. perf Pt 7 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Dai Rakuda Kan, Durham, N.C. perf Pt 8 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Dai Rakuda Kan, Durham, N.C. perf Pt 9 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Byakko Sha, Kyoto Mountain perf. Pt 1 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Byakko Sha, Kyoto Mountain perf. pt 2 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Byakko Sha, Kyoto Mountain perf. Pt 3 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Akiko Motofuji at Hijikata's Tomb (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Akiko Motofuji at Hijikata's Tomb steps, Hijikata period posters (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Ishii Pt. 2 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Ishii Pt 3, mt. (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Tenkei perf~ (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Ohno, Suiren perf. Pt 2 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Ohno, Suiren perf Pt 3 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Ohno, Suiren perf Pt 4 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Isamu Ohsuga, interv. Pt 2 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Oblique Strategist, Long version (PBS) 28:00 (Box 6, Folder 29)
    This videotape has not been distributed.
  - Meta Mayan II, Long version, with Holy Week 1993 re edit (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - As Is; (1984) revised 1985 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Meaning of the Interval (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - First edited video made by Vélez in 1970, very poor technical quality, B/W (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - On the Road to Atitlan (1977) very poor tech quality, B/W (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - Meta Mayan 11,20 mm. version 1981 (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - Tale, The Cuna Indians of San Bias, first version 1977 (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - AMosqueinTime(1990)8:00 1990 (Box 7, Folder 32)
  - Memory of Fire (1994) 23:00 shorter version than PBS one, currently in distnb. (Box 7, Folder 32)
  - Dance of Darkness( 1989) 56:00 (Box 7, Folder 33)
  - Sanctus, 10:00 mm (Box 7, Folder 34)
  - Phaedra (Ellen) 1974 2:30 (Box 7, Folder 34)
  - Rainbow 1974 5:00 (Box 7, Folder 34)
  - Andes, 3min (Box 7, Folder 34)
  - Pyramid 7 min (Box 7, Folder 34)
  - Gemini 3:00 min (Box 7, Folder 34)
  - Edin Vélez, self interview for Spanish TV (Box 7, Folder 34)
  - NHK TV program, includes a 15 min segment on Vélez (Box 7, Folder 35)
  - ArteSano del Siglo XX, arts prog Argentina, mostly about (Box 7, Folder 35)
  - Making "A Mosque in Time" production documentation (Box 7, Folder 36)
  - Making" Memory of Fire" production documentation (Box 8, Folder 37)
  - Making" Memory of Fire" production documentation (Box 8, Folder 38)
  - Making" Memory of Fire" production documentation (Box 8, Folder 39)
  - Making" Memory of Fire" production documentation (Box 8, Folder 40)
  - Making" Memory of Fire" production documentation (Box 8, Folder 41)
  - Maldng" Memory of Fire" production documentation (Box 8, Folder 42)
  - Making" Memory of Fire" production documentation (Box 9, Folder 43)
  - Making" Memory of Fire" production documentation (Box 9, Folder 44)
  - Making" Memory of Fire" production documentation (Box 9, Folder 45)
  - Making "A Mosque in Time" production documentation (Box 9, Folder 46)
  - Making "A Mosque in Time" production documentation (Box 9, Folder 47)
  - Making "A Mosque in Time" production documentation (Box 9, Folder 48)
  - Making "A Mosque in Time" production documentation (Box 10, Folder 49)
  - Making "A Mosque in Time" production documentation (Box 10, Folder 50)
  - Making "A Mosque in Time" production documentation (Box 10, Folder 51)
  - Butoh Videotapes, camera original dubs, part 2 (Box 10, Folder 51)
  - Byakko Sha, Kyoto Mountain perf. Pt 5 (Box 10, Folder 52)
  - Byakko Sha, Kyoto Mountain perf. p 6, Ohsuga int (Box 10, Folder 52)
  - Eiko and Koma, interv. (Box 10, Folder 52)
  - Ishii Interv (Box 10, Folder 53)
  - Ohno Perf Ikeda Museum, Yoshito Ohno interv (Box 10, Folder 53)
  - Butoh slow motions, test layerings for final edit (Box 10, Folder 53)
  - Hakutobo reh., Yoko Ashikawa, interv. (Box 10, Folder 54)
  - Takai Nakamura perform. Pt I (Box 10, Folder 54)
  - Takai Nakamura perform. Pt 2 (Box 10, Folder 54)
  - Ohno perf,, Ashikawa Archival perf. (Box 11, Folder 55)
  - Ashikawa solo, archival (Box 11, Folder 55)
  - Kaze No Kishki, Hijikata archival (Box 11, Folder 55)
  - Ohno very early performance films (1960's) (Box 11, Folder 55)
  - Mother Mallard's Portable Masrepiece company (1976) 30 min (Box 11, Folder 56)
  - Merian, 1975 (Box 11, Folder 56)
- Series 3. Fotos, Fotos are all 8 * 10" unless otherwise specified, all fotos are very high quality.
  - 1.MetaMayan, B/w: 4 production stills (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - 2.Tule, B/W: 2 portraits of Cuna women who are in the video Color2 portraits of Cuna women who are in the video (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - 3. Oblique Strategist ( Brian Eno Portrait), B/W; 4 production still with brian Eno (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - 4. As Is, B/W: 1 hiqh quality Monitor still (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - 5. Unique artists books ( handmade pop ups), B/W:3 photos of book pages (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - 6. Mosque In Time, B/W: 1 production still (Box 11, Folder 4)